Hi, this is Dr. Dan here and welcome
back to another video about chemistry.
So today we're going to be looking at
chemical equilibria which or chemical
equilibrium which what this has to do
with is looking at chemical reactions
and really how they're creating
reactants and products. So with these
types of reactions we are always looking
at a balance of both the forward
reaction and the reverse reaction. So
what exactly does that mean? Well, many
different reactions, one thing that we
will find out throughout chemistry is
that they are reversible. Meaning that
they don't only occur only in one
direction. So in previous videos and all
over the in probably in your chemistry
class, one thing that you saw that that
most of these reactions, they occur in
the forward direction. meaning that you
have reactants on the left hand side,
products on the right, and you see that
reaction created. However, a lot of
these different reactions as well have
can also go in the reverse. Meaning that
if reactants are colliding together to
make products, products could also be
colliding with each other as particles
to make reactants. So, you not only have
a forward, but you have a reverse
reaction as well. And this is what the
process of chemical equilibrium is all
about, which I'm going to show you in
this video and go through a lot of
different tips and tricks of really what
it is that you're going to be expecting
up up and coming. So, we're going to go
through examples and also do a bunch of
different things and show de scientific
demonstrations as well. So, please hit
that like and subscribe button and stay
tuned for more.
So now let's look at an actual chemical
example. So above me what you are seeing
is that we are mixing an iodine solution
with an acid. And this is called the
iodine clock reaction. And one thing
that you're seeing right now is that
colors are constantly changing. You see
it's going from this blue purple color
to clear and it's going back and forth.
Now what this is showing firsthand is
not only chemical equilibrium but also a
concept known as chemical kinetics as
well which is the speed of a reaction.
So what you are seeing is reactants are
going to products. So one it's going
from a blue color to a clear color and
you are seeing where the products get
converted back to the reactants. Meaning
that chemical equilibrium is this
dynamic con concept where not only are
we showing a forward and the reverse
direction but we also need to show that
we can have reversible reactions. So,
what you are going to be constantly
seeing is a double-sided arrow to show
that reactions are reversible, meaning
that they can go in both directions. So,
what are some different important things
that we need to know? Well, one of them
is a chemical equilibrium. When is it
achieved? Well, it's when the rate or
how fast are you making products or of
the forward reaction is equal to that of
the reverse reaction. So, making
reactants. So remember it's a
double-sided arrow. So when both those
are equal to each other, equilibrium is
achieved. We are achieving balance and
harmony. So that also means that the
ratio of the concentrations of both the
reactants and the products is now
considered to be constant and that's
when equilibrium is achieved. Now
depending on the level of chemistry that
you are taking hopefully that you get
one of the more simpler ones which we're
going to go through simple examples here
and then we'll have different different
future videos as well to go through
different example problems and harder
concepts.
Now where does that all start? Well that
all starts with the equilibrium
constant. Now the equilibrium constant
the way that that is generally
represented is with the letter K. So K
is something where it is a simple
formula where what we are doing is we're
taking the concentration of the products
and we're putting that all over the
concentration of the reactants.
So if I have a chemical formula, we will
be representing all these in
concentration or marity and we are going
to be raising these values to the power
of their coefficients.
Meaning that if I have let's say a
let's say if we have the following
formula. So if I have coefficients for
both reactants and products here. If I
had like a over a um so a is a
coefficient and a and big a is the is
the actual um chemical and that's
reacting with b and let's say that makes
c. Well, the way that we can show this
formula is products over reactants.
Meaning that I would put products. So I
put the product C up in top and then I
would put my reactants which would be A
raised to the power of A and my other
product B raised to the power B and that
would be equal to K. Now one thing about
K is that it comes in a bunch of
different ways and it represents
different meanings. So one thing is
depending on the size of your K value.
So if K is a constant, meaning it's a
number. If K is greater than one, it
favors the products, meaning if it's a
big number. If K is less than one, that
means it favors the reactants. And this
has to do directly with the
concentrations of each species at
equilibrium. So keep that in mind. And
if K is equal to one, that means that
both the reactants and the products are
equal to each other within these
reactions.
So how else can we also show this? Well,
K typically has a different subscript
that is next to it which represents
whatever type of reaction it is
describing. There are all kinds of
different K values. For example, you
could have where you have K a. this
represents an acid. You could have KB.
This could be tell talking about a base
dissociating.
You could have KC, which is all about
concentration.
You could have KQ,
which is just referring to equilibrium
within a reaction.
You could also have
uh Ksp
which talks about the solubility of a
different reaction. And if you've gone
through pH before then you might have
seen KW which is all about how water how
that dissociates. And then lastly you
could also have KP which is pressure. So
this is a lot of different equilibrium
constants and can get really
overwhelming. With most introductory
chemistry examples, you're usually going
to be sticking around maybe KC or
potentially
KQ as well, which these are usually
representing the same concept. Now, if
you're in in a more advanced chemistry
class, you probably will start seeing
KA's, KBs, and KWS. In general chemistry
2, KP and Ksp are going to be more
common. So what do we know about these K
values? Well, there's some important
rules. We can't only just write the
formulas products over reactants. The
one thing that only can be included in
here is that you can only include gases
and aquous phases of chemicals. You
never include solids and liquids when
you are going through this reaction. So
it's only gases and aquous mediums when
you are going through this. So let's try
and practice writing a couple different
expressions. So if I have the following
question, let's say if we want to write
a KC equation here. So first things
first is when we are going through this,
we're only going to be writing the KC
for products over reactants. So if I
look at my products, I see that I have F
minus as a product and that is aquous.
So we keep it. We have H3+
that is also aquous that is written on
top and notice how there's no
coefficients. So we do not have to worry
about writing a value here. They would
be represented by the value one being
the coefficients are one. So being that
is being said we also have in our
reactants we have HF and water. Well one
thing that you'll notice is that water
is a liquid. So based on our first rule,
we in our second rule, we do not include
water. So we're only going to have HF
as a product. And this would be the
answer for our question. Now, could this
only be represented as KC? Well, if you
might have maybe noticed is that HF is
an acid. So this could have also been
represented as K A and this would have
been a correct expression. So there are
multiple you could have more than one
answer for your K. As long as you're
representing it as an equilibrium
constant, you're okay. But keep in mind
there are there could be multiple
different possibilities.
Let's try another. What if I want to say
let's write the solubility product of
magnesium hydroxide, which tells you
that okay, what is solubility product?
Well, going back to previous videos of
solubility, which is all about, well, if
I have Mg
and I throw this in water, how is it
going to dissolve? So, if we have that
double arrow, the way that this is going
to dissolve, it's going to make its
individual ions. So we'll have magnesium
2+ and then two hydroxide
ions that are all going to be made in
solution. So being that these are
aquous,
these are our ions, but it's talking
about dissolving magnesium hydroxide. So
this is a solid or a precipitate. So if
we want to show this in our chemical
equation, well, we can do that as Ksp.
Now it's products over reactants. So
we'd have magnesium
2+
time hydroxide.
Now being that the p the coefficient for
hydroxide is two we would put a 2 power
above that. Now this is products over
reactants is the formula. However our
reactant in this case is a solid. So we
don't include it. It would only be
represented as the value of one assuming
that that gets taken out. So being that
that is just a one, we can safely just
erase, ignore and move our expression
down and show that the solubility is
affected by the concentrations
of both hydroxide and magnesium. And in
case you're wondering, don't forget that
these brackets, they represent
concentration. Meaning if you think of
concentration then going back to my
video on marity that is what that is
talking about is the marity of each of
these different species at equilibrium.
So
what if I asked you the following? If I
asked what is the Ksp for the reverse
precipitation
the reverse reaction precipitating out
magnesium hydroxide. So what does that
mean? So if we had the forward reaction
here, how could we show the reverse?
Meaning going backwards in this case. So
if we want to go backwards going to the
left hand side if we want to go back
well there's a couple ways you can think
about this is well one is going reverse
is also the same thing as saying Ksp
raised to the -1 for the previous
problem cuz you're going you're doing
the backwards or the inverse which means
is that instead we're going to have
reactants over products meaning
magnesium hydroxide
over magnesium and oxide. So if I
reverse this value, what this means is
that instead we'll have one cuz it's a
solid
over magnesium
2+ and hydroxide.
So this is you can reverse by doing the
inverse. So keep that in mind if you
need to talk about the other rate. They
should still show the same favoritism in
the reaction when you calculate the
value. So they'll either be showing that
maybe the product is going to be favored
or the reactant. They're both going to
be showing the same favoritism. Meaning
magnesium hydroxide if it's not very
soluble. Let's say if it exists as a
solid mainly then both reactions are
going to show favoring in the direction
of magnesium hydroxide. And that's what
that all means. So if K if the K value
let's say if K was less than one for
these well that tells you that oh this
is going to be favoring the reactants in
this reaction right whereas if I have
the inverse well being that that inverse
is representing the opposite equation of
magnesium 2+
making two hydroxide. So remember this
is all about reverse.
So if that's the case, that's going to
show how it's favoring the same side.
It's going to be favoring magnesium
hydroxide. And that's equilibrium for
you. It's about both directions going
back and forth until the concentrations
are constant. So this has been a video
on equilibrium. Please see that there'll
be future videos, one on Lhatier's
principle which will be soon and there
will be practice problems on how to
calculate K in the practice problem
series. All right, I hope this video
helped. If this did help, please like
and subscribe or comment below and I
hope to see you around for future
videos. Bye now.
[Music]